<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>St. Peter's sin and true repentance amplified and improved in a discourse occasion'd by the publick profession of repentance made by T.W., who after eleven years slavery in Turkey renounc'd his baptism and Christianity there ... / by John Shower.</title>
            <author>Shower, John, 1657-1715.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1692</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 47 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60148</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3684</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10197</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13776921</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13776921</idno>
            <idno type="VID">101761</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60148)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 101761)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 850:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>St. Peter's sin and true repentance amplified and improved in a discourse occasion'd by the publick profession of repentance made by T.W., who after eleven years slavery in Turkey renounc'd his baptism and Christianity there ... / by John Shower.</title>
                  <author>Shower, John, 1657-1715.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 36 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Samuel Wade ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1692.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Peter, --  the Apostle, Saint.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Luke XXII, 60-62 --  Sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:101761:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:101761:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>St. Peter's SIN, And <hi>True Repentance,</hi> Amplified and Improved IN A DISCOURSE Occaſion'd by the Publick Profeſſion of <hi>Repentance</hi> made by <hi>T. W.</hi> who after Eleven Years Slavery in <hi>Turkey,</hi> Renounc'd his Baptiſm and Chriſtianity there, and within a Year made his Eſcape, and returning firſt into <hi>Holland,</hi> deſired Solemnly to Acknowledge his <hi>Sin,</hi> and Profeſs his <hi>Repentance,</hi> which he did in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Church at <hi>Rotterdam, December</hi> the 3d 1687. where the following Sermon was then Preach'd.</p>
            <p>By <hi>JOHN SHOWER.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Samuel Wade</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> under the <hi>Royal Exchange</hi> in <hi>Cornhil,</hi> 1692.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb facs="tcp:101761:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:101761:2"/>
            <head>St. <hi>PETER</hi>'s SIN, And True REPENTANCE.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Luke 22.60, 61, 62.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And Peter ſaid, Man, I know not what thou ſayeſt. And immediately while he yet ſpake, the Cock crew. And the Lord turned, and looked upon Peter; and Peter remembred the word of the Lord, how he had ſaid unto him, Before the Cock crow, thou ſhalt deny me thrice. And Peter went out, and wept bitterly.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THere is ſome little Difference among the Evangeliſts, in the Hiſtorical Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of this Paſſage, of the Sin and Repentance of Saint <hi>Peter.</hi> But becauſe they
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:101761:3"/> give the ſame Account in Subſtance, though with a little variation one from the other, the one not knowing what the other had writ; 'tis an Argument that their Writings were not contrived by any Agreement with one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and that there was no Deſign among them to cheat the World with a falſe Story, their Teſtimony is thereby <hi>Diſtinct,</hi> and of the more Authority. Now though two of the Evangeliſts make mention of the Apoſtle <hi>Peters weeping bitterly;</hi> yet Saint <hi>Mark,</hi> who was the Companion, and Scholar, and Amanuenſis of <hi>Peter,</hi> and in whoſe Goſpel the primitive Church agree that he had a hand, when <hi>he</hi> ſpeaks of his Repentance, he only ſays, <hi>He wept;</hi> But when he ſpeaks of his Sin, he ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravates the Circumſtances of his Denial more than all the other Evangeliſts, <hi>He began to curſe, and to ſwear, I know not this Man of whom ye ſpeak,</hi> Mark 14.71. but gives the moſt modeſt Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of his Repentance, ſays not, that he <hi>wept bitterly,</hi> but that <hi>when He thought thereon, He wept.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:101761:3"/>
            <p>I would now, upon this Occaſion, ſpeak a little both to the <hi>Sin,</hi> and <hi>Repentance</hi> of this Apoſtle.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Let us conſider his <hi>Sin</hi> with its Ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravations.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The Truth and Evidence of his <hi>Repentance.</hi> That from both we may learn, for our Inſtruction and Practice, what ſuch a Diſcourſe is proper to teach us.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Concerning this <hi>Sin</hi> of the Apoſtle <hi>Peter,</hi> We may conſider both the Hiſtory of it according to the Evangeliſts, And the ſpecial Aggravations wherewith his Sin was cloathed.</p>
            <p n="1">1. We find an Account of this by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle <hi>Peter</hi> himſelf, <hi>Mark</hi> 14.54. as dictating to the Evangeliſt <hi>Mark</hi> the ſubſtance of his Goſpel, He tells us, that when our Lord was apprehended, and bound, and led away to Judgment, <hi>Peter</hi> followed him <hi>afar off,</hi> or at ſome Diſtance, to learn the Conſequence, and ſee the Iſſue of his Trial; and that he followed him to the High Prieſts Palace, or <hi>the High Prieſts Hall;</hi> that is, of <hi>Caiaphas,</hi> not his Father in Law <hi>Annas,</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:101761:4"/> who was the <hi>Sagan</hi> or Vicegerent under him, to ſupply his Place if there were Occaſion. The High Prieſts <hi>Hall,</hi> not the Room where the <hi>Sanhedrim</hi> met, but ſome outer Room through which they paſſed, ſcituated ſomewhat higher, ſo that the Company above might look down upon the Servants and Officers below.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Firſt</hi> Denial of Chriſt that the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> is guilty of, was upon the Queſtion of a Damſel that kept the Door, ſaying, <hi>Art not thou one of his Diſciples? Wert not Thou with Jeſus of Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lilee?</hi> To whom he replyes, <hi>I know him not,</hi> ſo one Evangeliſt hath it. <hi>I know not, neither under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand I what thou ſayeſt,</hi> ſays another Evangeliſt. And then he went out in the Court, and heard the Cock Crow, but takes no notice of that Warning.</p>
            <p>As to the <hi>Second</hi> Denial of Peter, After a little while another ſaith unto him, <hi>Thou alſo art One of them,</hi> and he denied With an <hi>Oath, I do not know the Man.</hi> At firſt he only diſowned his Diſcipleſhip, but now he adds an Oath to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm his lye.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:101761:4"/>
            <p>About an hour after he is challenged again, <hi>Verily Thou waſt with Jeſus of Galilee, Thou art a Gali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lean, and thy ſpeech be wrayeth thee.</hi> The Dialect of the <hi>Galileans</hi> comes nearer to that of the <hi>Samaritan</hi> or <hi>Syrian Idiom,</hi> than that of the Jews dwelling at <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> There is ſome Difference in all Nations in pronouncing the ſame Language, by thoſe who dwell in the chief Cities, and thoſe who inhabit in the remoter Provinces. They call him <hi>Jeſus of Galilee,</hi> as a Term of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, thereby denying him to be the true <hi>Meſsiah,</hi> who was to be born in <hi>Judea</hi> and not in <hi>Galilee: For out of Galilee ariſeth no Prophet, John</hi> 7.52. That is, There is no Record of any Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet that ever did ariſe from thence. The Chriſtians were uſually reviled by <hi>Julian</hi> the Apoſtate, under the Name of <hi>Galileans.</hi> But <hi>Peter</hi> denys that he appertains to <hi>Jeſus</hi> of <hi>Galilee,</hi> or of <hi>Nazareth.</hi> And then the whole Company joyn with Him who firſt ſuſpected him: For we read, <hi>That they that ſtood by ſaid; ſurely thou art One of them.</hi> And among the reſt, there happened to be One there, who was related to <hi>Malchus,</hi> whoſe ear <hi>Peter</hi> had ſmote off, and Chriſt had healed, as the Evangeliſt <hi>John</hi> relates it: And
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:101761:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſays, <hi>Did I not ſee thee in the Garden with him?</hi> But he denys it, and adds Curſing and Imprecation to gain credit to his perjury.</p>
            <p>He began to <hi>Curſe</hi> and to <hi>Swear,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Some think that he curſed Chriſt, but it is more likely he Anathematized himſelf, that is, wiſhed himſelf excluded from the Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue and the Church, if it were not true. Or, as others, that he wiſhed himſelf an Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Sepaartion from the Preſence of God; or, in the Jewiſh Phraſe, <hi>Let God do ſo to me, and more,</hi> if I am not a perfect ſtranger to the Man you talk of. He wiſhed in effect, that the Devil might take him, that God would deſtroy and damn him, if he were a Diſciple of Jeſus, or any way acquainted with Him. But our Lord looked back upon <hi>Peter,</hi> and the Cock crew a ſecond time, and then he remembred the words of Jeſus, ſaying, Before the Cock crow twice thou ſhalt deny me thrice; And he went out, and wept bitterly.</p>
            <p n="2">2. But before I ſpeak of his <hi>Repentance,</hi> Let us conſider a little of the Aggravation of his <hi>Sin.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:101761:5"/>
            <p>Firſt, from the <hi>Perſon</hi> who is thus guilty of denying Chriſt, In what Rank he ſtood, What Character he bore, and under what Obligations he was to have acted otherwiſe. It was <hi>Peters;</hi> Not an ordinary Diſciple, but an Apoſtle, One of the twelve, yea One of the chiefeſt of the Apoſtles, unto whom our Lord does often ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs his Diſcourſe, as to the Firſt and Principal of them. <hi>Peter,</hi> who had preached and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſied in the Name of Chriſt, who had wrought Miracles by his Power, caſt out Devils by vertue of his Commiſſion, yet He denys him. <hi>Peter,</hi> who was admitted to more than ordinary familiarity and Friendſhip with our Lord; who was not only of his own Houſe and Family, but had been favoured to be one of the three preſent at our Lords Transfiguration. <hi>Peter,</hi> who had hitherto forſaken all for the Intereſt of his Maſter, and hazarded his Life in his ſervice; who had vowed, proteſted, ſo lately, ſo ſolemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that though all ſhould deny him, yet he would not, but rather dye upon the ſpot than quit his Cauſe, or forſake his Company; Yet he denyes him. <hi>Peter,</hi> who was ſo fully ſatisfied that Jeſus was the Chriſt, the Son of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:101761:6"/> the living God, that he aſſerts and declares it in the Name of all the Diſciples, <hi>Math.</hi> 16. So that it might have been expected from him, that he ſhould have been an Example of courage and Conſtancy to all the reſt; Yet <hi>he</hi> denys and forſwears him, as if he had never ſeen him.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Conſider the Aggravations of his Sin, from the Perſon <hi>whom</hi> he denys. He diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>owns any Relation to <hi>Chriſt</hi> the true Meſſiah, whom to know is eternal Life. He denys any Acquaintance with him, who had obliged him ſo particularly, and by ſo many Inſtances of his kindneſs, who called him ſo ſtrangely from his Nets to be a Fiſher of Men; who had honoured him with a Commiſſion to preach the Goſpel, and confirmed it by Miracles; Who took him with <hi>James</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> to Mount <hi>Tabor,</hi> when he appeared in his Glory; who condeſcended to let him walk upon the waters, and when he was ſinking, to ſtretch forth his hand to ſecure him; Yet this kind and merciful Saviour he denys and diſowns, who had ſtooped but a little before to waſh <hi>Peters</hi> feet, who permitted him to ſit down with him at Table, to eat the Paſſover, and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:101761:6"/> take of the Sacrament of the Lords Supper; And but a few hours before he permitted him to ſee part of his Agony in the Garden, and charged him to <hi>watch</hi> and <hi>pray leſt he enter into Temptation,</hi> and awaked him three ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral times out of Sleep, with a Repetition of that command; <hi>Watch</hi> and <hi>Pray:</hi> Yea, but a little before he made the Multitude fall to the Ground by the force of a mild Expreſſion, <hi>I am He;</hi> and wrought a Miracle in his Sight, in the ſudden Reſtitution of <hi>Malchus</hi> Ear by a touch, which <hi>Peter</hi> had unadviſedly cut off: And yet after all this, he denies his Lord and Saviour, who had given ſuch proofs of his Divinity before his Eyes.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Conſider <hi>before whom</hi> he denies him, in what Company, before what Witneſſes: The Scribes, and Phariſees, and Chief Prieſts, and Elders of the Jews, could not but rejoyce, That One Diſciple of Chriſt ſhould betray him for money, and Another deny, and forſwear him through fear. The High Prieſts Servants, and the common People of the Jews, could not but be hardened and prejudiced againſt Chriſt and his Doctrine, by ſuch an Inſtance. And if
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:101761:7"/> there were any ſecret, hidden, half Diſciples, ſuch who were almoſt perſwaded to be Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans; it muſt needs ſhake and ſtagger their Faith, to find ſuch a One, as <hi>Peter,</hi> revolt ſo ſhamefully.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Conſider the <hi>ſmalneſs</hi> of the <hi>Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> eſpecially to his <hi>firſt</hi> Denial. A Damſel only asked him the Queſtion, whether he was not one of Chriſts Diſciples; and ſome think, rather out of <hi>Pity,</hi> than Reproach: And yet he feares to own it. Had the fight of Armed Souldiers, come to apprehend and ſeize him, put him into a fright; Had he been examined before the Sanhedrim, or terrified by the threatnings of the High Prieſt; Had he been bound, and led away to Judgment, before the Roman Deputy; Had there been a Proſpect of an ignominious painful Death, from the Roman Souldiers, As the Conſequence of his owning his Relation to Chriſt; ſomething might be pleaded on his Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half. But to diſown his Acquaintance with him, and Relation to him, at the queſtion of an inconſiderable Servant to the High Prieſt, that only kept the Door, the ſmalneſs of the Temptation was an Aggravation of the Fault.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:101761:7"/>
            <p>Fifthly, The <hi>Repetition</hi> of his Denial was an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other Aggravation of it. He not only denys him, but ſwears to it that he knows him not, he confirms it by an Oath, calls the God of Truth to bear witneſs to his Lye, That he knew not Chriſt, with vvhom he had converſed ſo long and ſo familiarly, and from whom he ſo lately parted. And again he denyes him with the Imprecation of a dreadful <hi>Anathema</hi> on him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, in caſe he aſſerted a Falſhood.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, How <hi>many other</hi> complicated <hi>Sins</hi> were implyed in this Fault of <hi>Peter?</hi> The higheſt Ingratitude to his Maſter, unpardonable Raſhneſs, in venturing into ſuch Company, and tarring there ſo long, and without a call making bold with Temptation: For our Lord had not appointed his Diſciples to follow him, but bad them Watch and Pray; He had diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſed them, and appointed a Place to meet af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his Reſurrection. There was likewiſe ſhameful Unbelief, in diſtruſting the Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, or the Power of Chriſt, to have aſſiſted him. There was a baſe Cowardiſe, To diſown him in ſuch a manner. And for a time, there was Impenitence and hardneſs of Heart, ſo as
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:101761:8"/> not to take the firſt Warning by the Crovving of the Cock, But vvhen the Cock crevv a <hi>ſecond</hi> time, <hi>Our Lord looked upon Peter, and he remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred the words of Jeſus, and went out, and wept bitterly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. He <hi>went out.</hi> Though <hi>Calvin</hi> and Others condemn him for going out, and think he had done better to have tarried, and ovvned his Maſter, in the preſence of that Company be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vvhom he had denyed him; Yet vvhen vve knovv that his Repentance vvas unfeigned, and accepted vvith God, We ought to put the beſt Conſtruction upon ſuch a Paſſage: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I vvould rather conſider it as a proof of his Repentance: For,</p>
            <p n="1">1. We may impute it to his <hi>Zeal,</hi> and <hi>Affection</hi> to Chriſt. Could he love him as he did, and be ſenſible of his guilt in having denyed him, and yet bear to ſee the outrage and Violence that vvas offered to his Maſter? Hovv can vve ſuppoſe, that he could indure to tarry in ſo deteſtable a Place, to be a Witneſs to the Affronts offered to his Lord! to hear him ſcorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and reviled, and reproached, and blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemed? This might make him retire from
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:101761:8"/> that wicked Crew, to mourn in ſecret.</p>
            <p n="2">2. We may aſcribe it to the greatneſs of his <hi>Remorſe</hi> and <hi>ſorrow,</hi> and penitent <hi>ſhame,</hi> for his late Apoſtacy. He could not but be greatly aſhamed of his Ingratitude to ſo good a Maſter, and bluſh to look him in the Face, Conſidering that he ſo lately denyed to have ever ſeen him. What elſe could be expected, but that ſhame and ſorrow would make him chooſe Retirement, to vent his Grief by Tears, and pour out his Soul before the Lord in ſecret? Solitarineſs is certainly moſt agreeable to an af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted Spirit, <hi>Iſay.</hi> 22.4. <hi>Look away from me, I will weep bitterly, labour not to comfort me, becauſe of the ſpoiling of the Daughter of my People. John</hi> 20.11. <hi>Mary ſtood without, at the Sepulcher, weeping.</hi> Unobſerved Privacy is moſt eligible under any great Paſſion of Grief or ſhame: But here is a Conjunction of both. It is an Argument of his Sincerity, to retire in ſecret to mourn. He cannot well be thought to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble his Grief, who chuſes no other Witneſs but the Omnipreſent God.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It may be attributed to his <hi>Prudence,</hi> and Diſcretion. Conſidering the Malice and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:101761:9"/> Fury with which they proceeded againſt Chriſt, he could not rationally expect if he were known to be a Diſciple of Chriſt by an open declaration of him, to meet with much better Entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment than his Maſter had; and thereby he might loſe the opportunity of teſtifying his ſincere Repentance, by his future Diligence and Reſolution in preaching the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>Beſides, what Service could he render his Maſter by ſo bold an Action? What Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was he under to hazard his Life, when there was no apparent Neceſſity to warrant his doing ſo? Eſpecially having ſuch late experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence or his own Weakneſs, notwithſtanding his former Reſolutions of Conſtancy. He was bound both in <hi>Prudence,</hi> and in <hi>Conſcience</hi> to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void Temptation, and therefore to quit the Place and Company, where he had met with the Temptation that occaſioned his Fall. He did well therefore, that he went out. But that is not all, For,</p>
            <p>Secondly, There is a ſecond proof of the ſincerity of his Repentance, Which, is his <hi>Bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter weeping;</hi> He went out, and wept bitterly. Not only is the ſecrecy and retirement that
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:101761:9"/> He choſe for his ſorrow, an Argument of his Sincerity; But we are likewiſe to conſider, That this his Grief was extraordinary, and his Tears abundant, As the Phraſe of <hi>weeping bitterly</hi> does import, and is ſo uſed in other Places, <hi>Iſay.</hi> 22.14. <hi>Chap.</hi> 33.7.<note n="*" place="margin">You that are come here to teſtifie your Repentance for having denyed Chriſt, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced your Faith in <hi>Turky,</hi> ought to take notice of this, and imitate the repentance of <hi>Peter</hi> as I hope you do.</note> Doubtleſs with his Tears, was joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a free and hearty con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of his Sin, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wailing his Folly, Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging his offence, Earneſtly imploring Pardon and Forgiveneſs For if his Grief was too big for words, we may well perceive the inward Remorſe of his Conſcience, and ſmart Reflections he made on himſelf, to ſome ſuch purpoſe as this,</p>
            <p>
               <q>O my Soul! What have I done? Have I denyed and abjured the Author of Eternal Life, for fear of a temporal Death? Did I not once acknowledge Chriſt to be the Son of the living God? And have I ſince denyed him with Oaths, and Curſes, and Imprecations? Did I not promiſe to lay down my Life for his ſake, and though all ſhould forſake him,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:101761:10"/> yet I would not; And have I yet diſowned and denyed him, at the voice of a Damſel? O what Unfaithfulneſs; what Weakneſs! what Wickedneſs! Thus to deny and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwear my Lord! Have I denied thee, O my Saviour! before the wicked<note n="*" place="margin">And you may ſay ſo as to the <hi>Mahometans</hi> and <hi>Turks.</hi>
                  </note> Jews? and may'ſt not thou juſtly deny me before thy Father and his Holy Angels? Did I diſown that I ever knew thee? And may'ſt not Thou, at the great Day, bid me depart amongſt the Workers of Iniquity; ſaying, I know you not. Did I joyn my ſelf in Company with thy Haters, and Deſpiſers, and Murtherers? And may I not be rejected, condemned, and puniſhed with them? O that my Head were a Fountain, that I might weep continually! That the Fault of one Night might be La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented by me all the days of my Life. Lord, was I not warned, and cautioned, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly foretold, that my Confidence would betray me, and let me fall? And yet ſo fool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh was I and ignorant, ſo heedleſs and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wary, ſo unmindful of thy Friendly Admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitions,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:101761:10"/> ſo forgetful of thy Monitory Predi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, as thus literally to fulfil it by my Triple Denial.</q>
            </p>
            <p>To this purpoſe we may ſuppoſe he did ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe and condemn himſelf, and that with the deepeſt Remorſe and Anguiſh of Spirit, which his Tears do more than intimate; owning himſelf an Apoſtate Wretch, a Condemned Malefactor, unworthy to live, a Son of Death; To whom the common Light of the World was too great a Favour, and outer, everlaſting Darkneſs a deſerved Portion.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, But this is not all: For he further teſtified his Repentance by his <hi>Carriage</hi> and <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">And you that now profeſs your Repentance here, for having renounced Chriſt and Chriſtianity, ought to take notice of this.</note> afterward. That in two Particulars. 1. By the lively Remembrance of that Sin, and Humble Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of it upon all Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions. 2. By more than ordinary forwardneſs and zeal, to teſtifie his Love to Chriſt and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagate the Faith of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p n="1">1. By the lively <hi>Remembrance</hi> of that Sin, and humble <hi>Confeſſion</hi> of it. It is reported in Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Hiſtory, that ever after, when this
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:101761:11"/> Apoſtle heard the Crowing of a Cock, he would either fall upon his knees, or in ſome other manner expreſs his Repentance, and bleſs God for his Recovery. Others ſay, that he was wont to riſe at Midnight, and ſpend the time between Cock-crowing and Day-light, in penitent Devotion. We find ſomthing agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to this in the Inſtance of <hi>David,</hi> after his Adultery and Murther, Pſal. 6.6. <hi>I made my bed to ſwim, and watered my Couch all night with my Tears.</hi> His <hi>Bed</hi> brought to Remembrance his Adultery with <hi>Bathſheba;</hi> and his <hi>Couch</hi> revived the Thoughts of his Murther of <hi>Uriah,</hi> For we find him on his Couch when he Signed the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der for the Death of <hi>Uriah.</hi> The <hi>Romaniſts,</hi> who are apt to turn every thing into Superſtition, began that practice of placing a <hi>Cock</hi> upon the top of Towers and Steeples, to put people in mind of this Sin of <hi>Peter,</hi> and his Repentance, by that Signal.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The truth of his Repentance was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed, by his extraordinary <hi>Zeal</hi> and <hi>Forward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> afterward, to expreſs his <hi>Love to Chriſt,</hi> and propagate the Chriſtian Faith. It is true, we do not find that after he went out from the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:101761:11"/> High Prieſts Hall, that ever he ſaw his Maſter again, till he was riſen from the Dead: But we find that he came early in the Morning on the Third day unto the Sepulcher, and was the <hi>Firſt</hi> that went down into it, <hi>John</hi> 20.6. And we find him deſirous to teſtifie a peculiar Affection to his Maſter, <hi>John</hi> 21. <hi>begin.</hi> For when <hi>Peter</hi> and the other Diſciples were fiſhing at the Sea of <hi>Tiberias,</hi> our Lord appears on the ſhoar. The Apoſtle <hi>John</hi> ſaid unto <hi>Peter, It is the Lord, ver.</hi> 7. Then <hi>Peter,</hi> to make haſte to meet him, only girts his Coat about him, and caſts himſelf into the Sea; while the other Diſciples, not above Two Hundred Cubits from Land, come by Ship to meet him. After a ſhort Dinner, it may be paſt in Silence; for we read in the <hi>Twelfth</hi> Verſe, that when Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus ſaid unto him, <hi>Come and Dine,</hi> yet none of the Diſciples durſt ask him, <hi>Who art thou?</hi> ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they knew he was the Lord. But <hi>Jeſus ſays unto Simon Peter, Loveſt thou me more than theſe?</hi> He anſwered, <hi>Yea Lord, thou knoweſt that I love thee.</hi> And being asked again, he replies, <hi>Thou know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt that I love thee.</hi> And being asked a <hi>third</hi> time, he anſwers, <hi>Lord, thou knoweſt all things, thou knoweſt
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:101761:12"/> that I love thee.</hi> Profeſſing his Love three ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral times, as he had been guilty of a Triple Denial.</p>
            <p>Whereupon our Lord minds him of what he had formerly ſaid, That when he was convert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed he ſhould ſtrengthen his Brethren; and therefore puts him upon this Evidence of his ſincere Repentance and Love to Chriſt, <hi>Feed my Lambs, Feed my Sheep.</hi> Though thou haſt denied and diſowned the Shepherd of thy Soul, yet feed my Sheep: Let this be the firſt Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of thy Love, which afterwards thou muſt confirm with the loſs of thy Life, and ſeal with thy Bloud. And by the Hiſtory of the Acts of the Apoſtles, we find his extraordinary Dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence to ſpread the Goſpel: For the Travels of this Apoſtle in his Miniſterial work, are computed to be above Nine Hundred and Fifty Miles.</p>
            <p>'Tis an Inſtance of the Wiſdom of Divine Providence, that this Apoſtle ſhould be ſent principally to Preach the Goſpel to the <hi>Jews,</hi> and be the Miniſter of the Circumciſion, who had thus joined with the Jews in diſowning Chriſt; that he ſhould endeavour to perſwade
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:101761:12"/> them to join with him in <hi>Repentance,</hi> as he had joined with them in Sin.<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Jackſon.</hi>
               </note> And the Parallel may be carried further, As the Nation of the Jews had known the Lord above all other People, had ſeen his Wonders, and been favoured by peculiar Inſtances of his Kindneſs, ſtood in ſpecial Relation to Him, and made the higheſt Profeſſion of Love and Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, and expected the coming of the Son of God; Yet when he came amongſt them, they diſowned his Authority, and proteſted againſt him, We have no King but <hi>Caeſar,</hi> &amp;c. So the Apoſtle <hi>Peter,</hi> though he had ſeen our Saviour, and lived in his Family, and been Witneſs to his Miracles; was nearly related to him, and profeſſed more than ordinary Affection and O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience; Yet he baſely diſowned him, when it came to the Trial. <hi>His Sin</hi> was in ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect like <hi>Theirs,</hi> and therefore he is the fitteſt Perſon to Preach the Goſpel to them. His Diligence therein is another Argument of the Sincerity of his Repentance.</p>
            <p>The Application follows; For <hi>Inſtruction,</hi> and <hi>Practice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:101761:13"/>1. From the very Relation of this Paſſage of the Scandalous Fall of one of the Apoſtles, and the particular Deſcription of it by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles themſelves, We may learn one Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to confirm the Truth of the Goſpel Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory. Had it been a Forgery, or Humane Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivance, theſe things would have been conceal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: But the Spirit of God has left this upon Record, to warn us againſt the like Sins, and to encourage the Repentance of thoſe that have fallen in an Hour of Temptation. We may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve farther</p>
            <p>From the Sin and Fall of this Apoſtle, What little Reaſon the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> has to boaſt of the pretended Succeſſion of their Popes to the Apoſtle <hi>Peter.</hi> They are his Succeſſors in denying Chriſt the Glory due to him as Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, but in vain do they pretend to be the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Biſhops of the univerſal Church as his Succeſſors. We read of no ſuch Superiority that <hi>Peter</hi> had over the reſt of the Apoſtles; Not till Chriſts Aſcenſion to be ſure, for then there would have been two heads of the Church. Nor afterward: For he was only the Apoſtle of the Circumciſion. And St. <hi>Paul</hi> the Doctor of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:101761:13"/> the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> withſtood him to the Face, and ordained Paſtors without him,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 2. and 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.5.</note> and tells us he was not inferiour to the chiefeſt Apoſtles. And <hi>Peter</hi> was ſent as a Meſſenger from the reſt of the Apoſtles, <hi>Acts</hi> 8.14. And when he was accuſed, he pleads his own Cauſe before the other Diſciples, and ſubmits to the Judgment of the Council, <hi>Acts</hi> 11. Moreover when there were Diviſions in the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> that ſome were for <hi>Paul,</hi> and ſome for <hi>Apollos,</hi> and ſome for <hi>Cephas,</hi> or <hi>Peter;</hi> We do not find the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> directs them to Center all in <hi>Peter;</hi> He owns no ſuch Authority and Supremacy in him above others, as the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> have inveſted him and his Succeſſors in. The Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> have imitated <hi>Peter</hi> too much in the Denial of Chriſt, but in little elſe that we know of. Again,</p>
            <p>From the Sin and Fall of <hi>Peter,</hi> We may obſerve the Subtlety of the Devil, to ſuit his Temptations to the particular Tempers of Men; and ſo to ſeaſon and time his Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, as to have the greateſt probability of Succeſs. He takes confident <hi>Peter</hi> in a fit of
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:101761:14"/> Fear at the Apprehenſion and Arraignment of his Maſter; who at another time would have replied to the Devil, as Chriſt did to him when he acted the Devils Part, <hi>Get thee behind me Satan.</hi> Our great Adverſary the Devil knows how to aſſault us with ſuitable Temptations, and in what Circumſtances we are moſt likely to yeild; we had therefore need to watch and ſtand upon our guard.</p>
            <p>We may alſo obſerve the Juſtice of God, in permitting the ſtrongeſt <hi>Confidence</hi> to be ſhamed and baffled. Let us therefore remember, that none are ſo likely to enter into Temptation, and be overcome, as thoſe who are leaſt afraid of it. None are more likely to fall, than thoſe who are moſt confident of their own ſtanding. None more ready to yeild to Temptation, than ſuch as preſume they ſhall never yeild. Moreover,</p>
            <p>In that after <hi>Peter</hi>'s firſt Denyal he heard the Cock crow, and did not take warning, we may learn, That whoever ſins againſt the Light of his own Mind and Conſcience, may be ſo far hardened and ſtupified by it, as that the plaineſt warnings, for a time at leaſt, ſhall be diſregar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, and have no influence. One would won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:101761:14"/> after what Chriſt had told him concerning his Denial before the Crowing of the Cock, that he did not recollect it when he firſt heard the Cock to Crow.</p>
            <p>We may further learn, That there is a Mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Fleſh and Spirit, of Corruption and Grace, in the beſt Saints. I doubt not, but <hi>Peter</hi>'s Reſolution to dye with Chriſt, rather than deny him, proceeded from a Principle of Grace and true Affection to his Lord. I que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion not, but he verily thought he ſhould do as he ſaid; but his Confidence of himſelf, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he preſumed on his own ſtrength, had a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful mixture with it, which occaſioned his Fall. It therefore concerns all, even the beſt men, that they <hi>watch and pray, leſt they enter into Temptation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But conſidering, That though the Sin of <hi>Peter</hi> was great, yet his Repentance was not long de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layed; We may compare it with ſome other In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances in Scripture, and obſerve, That <hi>Sins, by the ſurprizal of a ſudden Temptation, are much ſooner repented of, than where the Sin is preſumptuous, deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berate and contrived.</hi> Let us take the Inſtance of <hi>David,</hi> in the matter of <hi>Bathſheba</hi> and <hi>Uriah,</hi> and compare it with this Example of <hi>Peter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Peter</hi> knew ſo well that he ſhould not deny
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:101761:15"/> his Lord, that he was confident he never ſhould. He honoured his Maſter in his Heart, and came to the High-Prieſts Hall with a Reſolution of Conſtancy;<note place="margin">Biſhop <hi>Sanderſon.</hi>
               </note> but denied him, to decline a preſent apprehended Danger, under a violent Paſſion of Fear; Which was not ſo deliberate and preſumptuous a Sin, as <hi>David</hi>'s Adultery and Murther: For he contin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in his Adultery with <hi>Bathſheba</hi> for a long Time; and in order to the ſecrecy of it, gave command concerning the Death of <hi>Uriah</hi> the Husband; and that not in an haſty Paſſion, or in a ſudden ſurprize; but in cool blood, with many a deliberate thought about it. Now as there was a great difference in their Sin, ſo as to the time of their Recovery. St. <hi>Peter</hi> took the warning of the ſecond Crowing of the Cock, and immediately goes forth to expreſs his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance; but <hi>David</hi> continued almoſt a Twelve-Month without any ſolemn Repentance, that we read of, after ſuch a Fault, and till the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Nathan</hi> comes to him, and is forced to tell him, <hi>Thou art the Man.</hi> Again,</p>
            <p>From <hi>Peter</hi>'s taking the Warning of the <hi>ſecond</hi> Crowing of the Cock, when he was not awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened by the <hi>firſt,</hi> We may obſerve, <hi>That the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:101761:15"/> ſame Means, which men have had for a time and not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fited by, may yet, through the Bleſſing of God, be af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards effectual, if they be continued or vouchſafed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain.</hi> Let ſuch as have long enjoyed the Means of Grace, and have not profited, bleſs God that they are yet continued, and beg the Influence of the Spirit, that at length they may be effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al. You that for many years have ſat under the Preaching of the Word, that every Lords Day, and frequently on the Week Days, are called to Repentance, and yet have been unprofitable Hearers hitherto; you ought not to forbear your Attendance on the Publick Worſhip, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the ſame Truths which have been heard at one Time with little Profit, at another may come with Power and Efficacy to your Souls.</p>
            <p>Laſtly. You may take notice of the Mercy and Love of Chriſt to his poor Diſciple, and of his Faithfulneſs to his Promiſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. His <hi>Mercy</hi> and <hi>Love</hi> to his poor Diſciple. He forgets not <hi>Peter,</hi> when He himſelf was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended and brought to Judgment, amidſt the Calumnies and falſe Accuſations, the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries and Indignities which our Lord met with, yet he remembers <hi>Peter,</hi> and turns about, and gives him a gracious Look, that melted his
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:101761:16"/> Heart, and recals him to Repentance. Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly he hath not leſs Kindneſs for his Follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers now he is in Heaven, than he had while he was upon Earth.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Obſerve his <hi>Faithfulneſs</hi> to his <hi>Promiſe,</hi> and the <hi>Prevalency</hi> of his <hi>Prayer</hi> for <hi>Peter. Satan,</hi> ſays our Lord, <hi>has deſired to have thee, and to ſift thee as wheat; but I have prayed for thee, that thy Faith fail not, Ver.</hi> 31. of this Chapter. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore though he was permitted to Fall, to hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble him for his Confidence, and to warn us by his Example, and to teach more Watchfulneſs and Circumſpection; yet his Faith did not fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally fail, but he is recovered again by a ſpeedy and deep Repentance. And there is no true Chriſtian but is intereſted in this Promiſe, and ſhall ſhare in the Prevalency of the Interceſſion of Chriſt: His Faith ſhall not finally fail; He that hath begun a good Work, will carry it on: He that is the Author of Divine Faith, will be the Rewarder and Finiſher of it.</p>
            <p>For Direction as to <hi>Practice.</hi> From what has been ſaid, we may learn</p>
            <p n="1">1. To take heed of the <hi>Beginnings</hi> of Sin. If the Devil have once got the advantage of <hi>Peter,</hi> by his <hi>firſt</hi> Denial of Chriſt, he ſhall quickly be tempted
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:101761:16"/> to deny him again; If he yield to one Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, he ſhall ſoon meet with more and ſtronger. At firſt only a Damſel asks the Queſtion, but af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards the whole Company accuſe him as a Follower of Chriſt. He that will venture upon a Lye, ſhall be tempted to tell another to conceal the firſt, and to add Perjury and Imprecation to prevent diſcovery. The breaking of our good Purpoſes and Reſolutions in one Inſtance, will make way for our doing ſo in many others. As <hi>David</hi> from Adultery proceeded to Murther, and <hi>Lot</hi> from Drunkenneſs to Inceſt; and <hi>Peter</hi> here from a bare Denial to Perjury, and Curſing, and Imprecation. The admiſſion of one Link of a Chain will make way for more. And without watching againſt the beginnings of Sin, they will ſoon multiply; as one curling Circle in the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter produces a ſecond, and ſo a third, of a larger ſize and figure than it ſelf. When you yield to any Temptation of the Devil, you know not where you ſhall ſtop, you give him an advantage againſt you, you Weaken and Harden your own Hearts, ſtifle Conſcience, and lay your ſelves more open unto Temptation, and your Reſiſtance will ſtill be weaker.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Let us heartily pity thoſe, who by the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:101761:17"/> ſurpriſe of a great Temptation have ſinned like <hi>Peter,</hi> in denying their<note n="*" place="margin">We have a ſad In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of one of our Country-men, now before us, who renounc'd his Baptiſm and Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in an hour of Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> Lord. Let us not preſently cenſure and condemn them of <hi>the Sin againſt the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> or of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning wilfully after the Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Truth, in ſuch a manner, as that it ſhould be impoſſible for them to be renewed again to Repentance. Let us ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther pray for them, that it be not <hi>a Sin unto Death,</hi> Eſpecially when we have any Inſtance of their<note n="*" place="margin">As we have in the preſent Caſe.</note> Repentance: For the Sin unto Death, and the Sin againſt the Holy Ghoſt, exclude <hi>Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,</hi> ſuch as are guilty do never repent.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Let us not be high-minded, but fear; and while we ſtand, take heed leſt we fall.</hi> Did an Apoſtle, and ſo great an Apoſtle, Deny and Forſwear his Lord? and that ſo ſoon after he had been at <hi>the Lords Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</hi> which was but the Night before, or but ſome few hours before? And ſhall any of us be confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of our own Courage and Conſtancy? How many Inſtances are there of thoſe who have ſhamefully fallen in an hour of Temptation, of ſuch as have renounc'd their Chriſtianity in <hi>Turky</hi> and received the Impoſtures of <hi>Mahomet;</hi> Of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:101761:17"/> many more in <hi>Popiſh</hi> Countries, that have abjured the Reformed Religion, to comply with the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitions and Impurities of <hi>Rome?</hi> Many ſuch there are, who once thought themſelves as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely to do ſo, as any of us can now think that we are: And ſhall we be Poſitive and Certain, Confident and Preſumptuous, that, though we had all their Temptations, we ſhould not do as they? Had not <hi>Peter,</hi> think you, more Reaſon to think and hope well of himſelf, and to believe that he ſhould <hi>rather Dye with Chriſt, than Deny him;</hi> than any of us have? Thanks be to God, you do not yet meet with the Temptations that others have experienced, and that there is no near pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect that you ſhall meet with ſuch Temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; yea I rejoyce in the hope that many of us would be aſſiſted and enabled by God, rather to dye for Chriſt, than deliberately to abjure, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny him; But let us not be confident in our ſelves; The Inſtance of this Text ſhould make us hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and cautious, and fill us with <hi>a Holy Fear,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they who are able to ſtand their ground againſt ſome ſorts of Temptation, may yield and be overcome by others.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Let us all reflect with ſhame and ſorrow up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our ſelves, That in too great a degree we have
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:101761:18"/> 
               <hi>imitated</hi> the <hi>Sin</hi> of <hi>Peter.</hi> We have denied our Lord as well as he; tho' not after the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, yet with as high Aggravations, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times more criminal ones. Have we not denied Chriſt by our Actions, though not by our Words? By having a form of Godlineſs, but denying the Power of it: <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.16. By profeſſing to know God and Chriſt, when in Works we deny and diſhonour him, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.5. We have not been ſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from the Profeſſion of his Name and Truth, by threatening Dangers, and the fear of Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; yet have we not forſaken and diſowned him, by the Luſts of the Fleſh, the Luſts of the Eyes, and the Pride of Life, contrary to our Baptiſmal Covenant? Though we are not Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates by a formal Abjuration of his Holy Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as to Doctrine and Worſhip; yet do we not practically contradict the Principles and Rules of it?</p>
            <p>Do you not deny him to be <hi>King,</hi> by not kiſſing his Scepter, ſubmitting to his Authority, and keeping his Commandments; by not walking as his Servants and Subjects, in univerſal Faithful Obedience, according to the Oath and Covenant we are under. Do you not deny him to be the Great <hi>High-Prieſt,</hi> by not depending on his
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:101761:18"/> Meritorious Righteouſneſs, and prevailing In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion, as the Ground of your Acceptance with God, for Pardon of Sin and Eternal Life? Do you not Deny him to be the Great <hi>Prophet,</hi> by choſen Ignorance, and wilful unbelief, under all the Teachings of his Word, and Spirit? Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the bright Revelation of his Goſpel that we injoy, and have ſo long injoyed? Do we not deny and diſown him to be our <hi>Lord,</hi> and <hi>Head,</hi> and <hi>Captain,</hi> and <hi>Saviour,</hi> by thwarting his Example, and refuſing to walk in his Steps? For Inſtance, by <hi>Drunkenneſs</hi> and <hi>Gluttony,</hi> when He was the greateſt Example of <hi>Temperance</hi> and exact <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briety:</hi> By <hi>Haughtineſs</hi> and <hi>Pride,</hi> when he has left us a Pattern of the deepeſt <hi>Humility:</hi> By <hi>Covetouſneſs</hi> and <hi>Uncharitableneſs,</hi> and want of <hi>Compaſſion</hi> to the Poor; when <hi>Charity,</hi> and <hi>Love,</hi> and <hi>Kindneſs</hi> towards all was exemplified in his whole Courſe.</p>
            <p>Yea there are many who profeſs themſelves <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> who not only <hi>Deny Chriſt,</hi> as <hi>Peter;</hi> but <hi>betray</hi> him, as <hi>Judas.</hi> Who ſell their Conſciences for Temporal Profit, and the gain of a little Money; Who undervalue the Bloud of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer, and all the Riches of his Grace, <hi>for thirty pieces of Silver;</hi> preferring their Eaſe, and Honour, and Wealth, before his Preſence and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:101761:19"/> Favour, &amp;c. Who is there, <hi>my Brethren,</hi> that has not in ſome ſenſe ſinned <hi>like Peter,</hi> with <hi>the like Ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravations</hi> as his Fault was attended with? Have we not ſinned <hi>after</hi> the <hi>knowledge</hi> of the Truth, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter we have confeſſed that <hi>Jeſus</hi> is the <hi>Lord,</hi> after we have owned him to be <hi>our Lord,</hi> and <hi>our Jeſus; after</hi> we have promiſed and proteſted by <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> and frequently ſince by the repetition of that Covenant at <hi>the Lords Table,</hi> that we would obey and ſerve him as long as we live? Have we not denied and diſhonoured him, <hi>after</hi> we have been adopted into the Family of God, and enjoyed the Priviledges of his Houſe; <hi>after</hi> eminent and ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Mercies, and peculiar Favours, as well as <hi>Peter; after</hi> we have been convinced, and awaken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and reſolved, and begun well, and held out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Temptation for a little while? Have none of us <hi>after this</hi> revolted from Chriſt, and returned to folly? Have you not retracted your vow, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicted your Experience, diſhonoured the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Name by which you are called, and denied the Lord of Glory, that ſo willingly was a Sacrifice for you? Yea have you not been called to Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance again and again, by the Preaching of the Word, as well as <hi>Peter</hi> by the crowing of the Cock, and yet remain impenitent to this Day?</p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:101761:19"/>
            <p>Nay further, Many of our <hi>Sins</hi> are <hi>more aggravated</hi> than the Sin of <hi>Peter, Peter</hi> denied Chriſt, it is true; but it was in the Houſe of <hi>Caiaphas:</hi> But ſome of us deny him even in his own Houſe and Temple. <hi>Peter</hi> denied him, but it was in the midſt of <hi>Enemies;</hi> But we do ſo in his own <hi>Family,</hi> amongſt his Diſciples, and Children, which is an higher Aggravation of our Sin, than his<note n="*" place="margin">And this poor Man in <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Slavery, under great and ſore Temptations, which he long reſiſted.</note>. <hi>Peter</hi> denied him, but it was when his Spirit was overwhelmed with fear, and ſurprizing Trouble; Whereas we deny and diſobey him, in the midſt of Peace and Plenty. <hi>Peter</hi> denyed him, but it was under the Apprehenſion of a Temporal and cruel Death, that might be the Conſequence of Owning him; But bleſſed be God we have no ſuch Temptation: On the contrary, if we deny him, it is in deſpight of the threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ening of temporal and eternal Death. So that our Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacy from Chriſt, and practical denyal of him, is more criminal in ſeveral reſpects, than the Fault of <hi>Peter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly. Therefore as we have imitated his <hi>Sin,</hi> let us imitate him in his <hi>Repentance</hi> too. We have heard that the <hi>Second</hi> Call awakened him to <hi>Repentance,</hi> when our Lord looked upon him; But how many Calls from God have ſome of us had? how often hath Chriſt looked upon and ſpoke to us? and knocked at the Door of our Hearts by his Spirit? Shall we not then obey his Voice to repent? As ſoon as <hi>Peter</hi> remembred his Sin, you have heard that he left the <hi>Place</hi> where he contracted his guilt, he avoided the <hi>Company</hi> that had been a ſnare to him. Oh imitate him in this, continue not to frequent ſuch <hi>Places,</hi> and ſuch <hi>Company,</hi> where you have been enſnared, and defiled, and met with prevailing Temptations to ſin.</p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:101761:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Concerning <hi>Peter</hi> you have heard, that he expreſſed his <hi>Repentance</hi> by bitter <hi>Weeping;</hi> Oh imitate him in this, and not only <hi>ſay</hi> you are ſorry, but give ſome convictive <hi>Sign</hi> and <hi>Evidence</hi> of it, that you do in earneſt <hi>Repent,</hi> and bring forth fruits meet for Repentance. Concerning <hi>Peter,</hi> you have heard that he manifeſted the <hi>truth</hi> of his <hi>Repentance,</hi> by his future zeal and Diligence, by his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Love to Chriſt, and Concern for his Honour, and Fidelity in his Service: O follow his <hi>Example,</hi> if you would ever have the Comfort and Reward of <hi>unfeigned Repentance;</hi> and not onely ſin no more, but be doubly <hi>diligent</hi> in circumſpect, and holy walking.</p>
            <p>'Tis ſad to conſider, how much <hi>formal, ſuperficial, coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit Repentance</hi> there is in the World. Men ſay they are ſorry they have done amiſs, they acknowledge their Faults, and it may be fetch a ſigh, or mutter a Groan, or drop a Tear, in a ſerious mood, or upon ſome ſolemn occaſion; But in <hi>a few Days,</hi> it may be ſooner, are the <hi>ſame</hi> again; The Convictions, and ſerious Impreſſions, they had upon <hi>the Lords-day,</hi> are very often loſt and gone before the return of the <hi>next Sabbath;</hi> The Vows and Reſolutions they make at <hi>the Lords Table,</hi> are not remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred and obſerved for an entire <hi>Moneth,</hi> but there is ſad work for a new Repentance, before the monthly Seaſon comes about. After ſolemn Profeſſions of <hi>Repentance,</hi> they are as bold and venturous upon Temptation as ever, as unmindful of their holy vows as ever; as careleſs and fearleſs, and ſo as eaſie a Prey to the Devil, as before. Have you not reaſon to reflect upon this? and therefore to go home, and weep bitterly, as <hi>Peter</hi> did? This would be a happy improvement of <hi>this Example.</hi> The Lord grant it may have ſuch Effects. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
